Guide to the Laurence Heyworth Collection of English Religious Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Laurence Heyworth collection of English religious manuscripts
1550-1820
1650-1710
OSB MSS 172
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.2
(73 boxes)
The collection consists of 73 volumes, mostly in English, containing sermons, sermon-notes, prayers, religious reflections, tracts, commonplace books, Biblical commentaries, and other religious and theological texts, mostly from the later seventeenth and early eighteenth centuries. Almost half of the volumes include sermons or sermon notes. Most authors are unidentified, but identified authors include John Nicholas, John Henderson, and William Barton. Devotional works include William Chilcot's Practical Treatise Concerning Evil Thoughts; an English version of Dominique Bonheur's Pensées chrétiennes; and The Life of Mr. De Marsay and his Wife, an extensive spiritual autobiography by a Quietist and mystic. Volumes documenting the spiritual and devotional lives of women include A Comfortable Companion for Afflicted Souls, being a threefold discorse collected out of Scripture by a woman; the notes of Sarah Meadows on methods of raising devout children, drawn from her own experience as a mother; the commonplace book of Frances Drake; and the spiritual biography of Sarah Kirshaw.There are also several Roman Catholic works, including one by the English Benedictine Augustine Baker, as well as two works documenting the Scottish Church and the Covenanters.
Heyworth, Laurence
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Laurence Heyworth, 1995-1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Laurence Heyworth Collection of English Religious Manuscripts consists of 73 volumes, mostly in English, containing sermons, sermon-notes, prayers, religious reflections, tracts, commonplace books, Biblical commentaries, and other religious and theological texts, mostly from the later seventeenth and early eighteenth centuries.
Almost half of the volumes include sermons or sermon notes. Most authors are unidentified, but identified authors include Joseph Hallett, John Nicholas, Thomas Allen, Andrew Grey, John Henderson, and William Barton. Many sermons in these volumes are annotated with dates and/or place of preaching. Other notable items containing sermons include the volume in Box 27, which includes sermons on the execution of Charles I and the restoration of Charles II, and the volume in Box 49, containing sermons preached at Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge. Information on the Scottish Church and on the Covenanters can be found in Boxes 37 and 44.
Devotional works include John Ingram's Exposition of ye Catechisme; an English version of Pietro Matteo Petrucci's Lettere e trattati spirituali e mistici (Box 26); William Chilcot's Practical Treatise Concerning Evil Thoughts (Box 62); and an English version of Dominique Bonheur's Pensées chrétiennes titled Christian Thoughts for every Day of the Month (Box 56). There are a number of commonplace books, including several that contain religious and inspirational poetry, including the commonplace books by unidentified authors in Boxes 15 and 41 and the volume in Box 25, which was probably written by a chaplain in the English Army during the Williamite War. Box 61 contains The Life of Mr. De Marsay and his Wife, an extensive spiritual autobiography by a Quietist and mystic.
Several works attest to the post-Reformation survival of English Roman Catholicism, including a 17th century manuscript in Latin containing rules of conduct for monastic life (Box 2); the Latin Rite prayer book on parchment in Box 16, which may have belonged to the recusant Howard family; the Prayer to the Sacred Virgin Mother Against the Plague in Box 19; and the copy of a work on the English Benedictine Mission by the Benedictine Augustine Baker (Box 55). Volumes documenting the spiritual and devotional lives of women include A Comfortable Companion for Afflicted Souls, being a threefold discorse collected out of Scripture by a woman (Box 12); the notes by Sarah Meadows on methods of raising devout children, drawn from her own experience as a mother (Box 43); the commonplace book of Frances Drake (Box 89); and the spiritual biography True relation of my sister Sarah Kirshaw her life [and] death. Who dyed at Poppleton neare Yorke. Janr.20.1656. Ano aetatis 21.
Arrangement
The manuscript volumes are organized by their original Heyworth MS numbers or letters; as the library did not receive every item in the Heyworth collection, there are gaps in the numbering and lettering sequences. Unnumbered items are listed in no particular order at the end of the finding aid.
Catechetical sermons -- Early works to 1800; Catholics -- England -- Early works to 1800; Christian life -- Early works to 1800; Conduct of life -- Early works to 1800; Covenanters -- Early works to 1800; Devotional literature, English; Devotional literature, English -- Early works to 1800; Dissenters, Religious -- England; English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700; English poetry -- 18th century; English prose literature -- Early modern, 1500-1700; English prose literature -- 18th century; Occasional sermons -- Early works to 1800; Prayers -- Early works to 1800; Quietism -- Early works to 1800; Religious education of children; Religious literature, English; Sermons, English -- 17th century; Sermons, English -- 18th century; Women authors, English; Great Britain -- Religion; Great Britain -- Religious life and customs; Commonplace books; Sermons; Baker, Augustine, 1575-1641; Barton, William, 1598?-1678; Bonheur, Dominique; Chilcot, William, 1663 or 1664-1711; Heyworth, Laurence; Kirshaw, Sarah; Marsay, Charles Hector de Saint George, marquis de, 1688-1753; Meadows, Sarah, 1654-1688; Church of England
- Untitled manuscript containing sermons, [16--] (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Heyworth MS 1
- Untitled manuscript, in Latin, containing rules of conduct for the monastic life [England], [16--] (Box 2)
  Heyworth MS 3
  Bound in manuscript waste.
- Untitled manuscript containing religious notes, [16--] (Box 3)
  Heyworth MS 4
- Camborne, Robert. Sermons and sermon notes, 1636 (Box 4)
  Heyworth MS 5
- Ingram, John. Exposition of ye Catechisme, 1673-1678 (Box 5)
  Heyworth MS 6
- [ Leicester's commonwealth ?], 1620s (Box 6)
  Heyworth MS 7
- Harpur, Henry. Commonplace book containing a collection of moral tales and reflections drawn principally from Sir Thomas More, Sir Walter Raleigh, Jeremy Taylor, and Causinus, 1674-1675 (Box 7)
  Heyworth MS 9
- Untitled manuscript containing prayers, apparently keyed to the Psalms, and other notes, [16--] (Box 8)
  Heyworth MS 13
- Lectures at Stroud: volume containing lectures and sermons, 1653 (Box 9)
  Heyworth MS 14
- A Concordance of the Chief Heads of Scripture Common-placed: manuscript volume in several hands, [16--] (Box 10)
  Heyworth MS 15
- Untitled manuscript containing meditations on a version of the Roman Catholic mysteries of the Rosary, [16--] (Box 11)
  Heyworth MS 16
- A Comfortable Companion for Afflicted Souls, being a threefold discorse collected out of Scripture by a woman: manuscript in a single hand of a religious text partly composed of linked passages from the Bible, 1684? (Box 12)
  Heyworth MS 17
  Ownership inscription on front flyleaf: Sarah Seawell? her Book
- Diary containing entries concerning attendance at services and sermons and the author's spiritual life., 1775 January-October (Box 13)
  Heyworth MS 18
- Hallett, Joseph, 1692?-1744. Untitled manuscript containing sermons, circa 1720? (Box 14)
  Heyworth MS 19
  Attributed to Hallett in acknowledgement list.
- Untitled manuscript containing 31 poems, in an unidentified hand, circa 1700 (Box 15)
  Heyworth MS 31
  Includes "The Misery of Mankind," "The Advantage of Thinking," "Death," "The Death of Christ," "Heaven," "The World," "Hell," and others.
- Howard family? prayer book, in an unidentified hand, in Latin, 1650? (Box 16)
  Heyworth MS 32
  Compilation of prayers for family use, with the Office of Benediction.
  General note
  On parchment.
- Calverley, John. Commonplace book containing selections from Eikon Basilike; a Latin version of the Carmina Aurea of Pythagoras; and mottoes from Wither's Emblemes, in a single hand, in English, Latin, and Greek, 1666 (Box 17)
  Heyworth MS 35
- Forrester, Archibald. Untitled manuscript containing religious works, 1684-1695? (Box 18)
  Heyworth MS 37
- Prayer to the Sacred Virgin Mother, called the miraculous prayer against the Plague, in an unidentified hand, [16--] (Box 19)
  Heyworth MS 39
- Heereboord, Adrianus, 1614-1661. Collegium Ethicum or Part of Heereboord's Morall Philosophy in English. ..by Thomas Gleane Esquire., 1668 (Box 20)
  Heyworth MS 40
  With a dedicatory epistle to Peter Gleane.
  Binding: full black morocco, highly decorated in paneled gilt, with central monograms in red morocco; compartmented spine, also gilt.
- Diary concerning religion, in French, English and shorthand, circa 1720 (Box 21)
  Heyworth MS 48
- Campbell, Archibald, d. 1744. Doctrines of a Middle State between Death and Resurrection, printed version, with manuscript additions and corrections by Campbell for a planned third edition: London, W. Taylor, 1721 (Box 22)
  Heyworth MS 53
- True relation of my sister Sarah Kirshaw her life [and] death. Who dyed at Poppleton neare Yorke. Janr.20.1656. Ano aetatis 21, manuscript, corrected, in a single hand (Box 23)
  Heyworth MS 55
- Commonplace book containing extensive quotations from Classical authors, in Latin and English. Headings include Poesia, Philosophia, Medicina, and Morbis., 1664-1688 (Box 24)
  Heyworth MS 58
  Armorial bookplate of Robert Spearman of Oldacres, Esq. Durham.
- Commonplace book concerning religion, in English and Latin, 1690 (Box 25)
  Heyworth MS 59
  Pencil annotation on front pastedown: Possibly kept by a chaplain in Williamite army.
- Petrucci, Pietro Matteo, 1636-1701. Some Short, Spiritual & Holy Letters written by Petrucci Bishop Jesi with some Ejaculatory acts of Diverse Virtues, All very helpful to advance one towards perfection, translation into English of Petrucci's Lettere e trattati spirituali e mistici, 1690-1700 (Box 26)
  Heyworth MS 63
- Collection of manuscript sermons and lectures. Includes a sermon on the anniversary of Charles II's restoration; one on the anniversary of the execution of Charles I; Lectures Upon The Church Catechism; and Sermons Concerning Prayer, 1683 May 29 (Box 27)
  Heyworth MS 64
- Dyke, W?. Autograph letter, probably addressed to his congregation, concerning religion and fortitude during earthly trials. Dated from Watford, 1640? Sep 20 (Box 28)
  Heyworth MS 68
- Commentary on the New Testament, in a single hand, circa 1660-1675 (Box 29)
  Heyworth MS 69
  Ownership inscription on front flyleaf: Liber Jacobi Tayloris, Donum Geo: Brentnall. Oddston, Leicestersh.
- De Votis, manuscript devotional pamphlet containing sections headed "The Vows" and "Brief considerations upon ye vows", [16--] (Box 30)
  Heyworth MS 70
- Untitled collection of eleven sermons, including three on The Passion and six on the Resurrection, undated (Box 31)
  Heyworth MS 71
- Untitled collection of sermons, circa 1720 (Box 32)
  Heyworth MS 72
- Untitled collection of twenty sermons, 1669 (Box 33)
  Heyworth MS 73
- Untitled collection of prayers, devotions, and sermons, [17--] (Box 34)
  Heyworth MS 77
- Nicholas, John. Seven sermons: Salisbury, 1700-1708 (Box 35)
  Heyworth MS 78
- Allen, Thomas, 1603-1673. Two sermons, 1667 (Box 36)
  Heyworth MS 83
- Untitled collection of sermons relating to the Scottish Church: [Scotland], circa 1679 (Box 37)
  Heyworth MS 84
  Includes two sermons by Andrew Gray, two sermons by Samuel Rutherford, and an incomplete breviary.
- Untitled collection of sermons, [165-] (Box 38)
  Heyworth MS 86
- Untitled collection of sermons, with an unidentified family genealogy, [165-] (Box 39)
  Heyworth MS 87
- Commonplace book containing copies of poems by Addison, Goldsmith, Pope, and others, [175-] (Box 40)
  Heyworth MS 89
- Commonplace book containing copies of poems by Pope and others; a collection of prayers; and medical recipes and accounts, 1734 (Box 41)
  Heyworth MS 90
- Annotations Upon the Holy Bible, printed version (2nd volume, Psalms to Apocrypha, pages 321-740), with manuscript annotations, circa 1651 (Box 42)
  Heyworth MS 91
- Meadows, Sarah, 1654-1688. Manuscript copy of her notes on raising devout children, in the hand of her husband Thomas Meadows, 1687 (Box 43)
  Heyworth MS 92
- Henderson, John. Untitled collection of Scottish sermons and testimonies by Covenanters, circa 1690 (Box 44)
  Heyworth MS 93
- Collection of sermons taken out of ye Manuscripts of ye Revd. Mr. John Wooddeson. M. A. Late Rector of Radnage Bucks, circa 1681 (Box 45)
  Heyworth MS 94
- Untitled collection of sermons: Somerset, Gloucestershire, 1688-1707 (Box 46)
  Heyworth MS 95
- Untitled collection of sermons, notes, and reflections, circa 1684 (Box 47)
  Heyworth MS 96
- Untitled collection of sermons, with an index: St. Mary's Church, Beverley, circa 1670-1690 (Box 48)
  Heyworth MS 97
- Untitled collection of sermons, texts, and records of assistance: Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge, 1699-1700 (Box 49)
  Heyworth MS 98
- Untitled collection of sermons, circa 1680 (Box 50)
  Heyworth MS 99
  Ownership inscription on front pastedown: William Valentine, Whixley Vicarage
- Commonplace book kept by an Anglican reader, with headings in Latin and authorities cited in the margin, [16--] (Box 51)
  Heyworth MS A
- Untitled collection of sermons and religious texts: [England], [16--] (Box 52)
  Heyworth MS B
  Includes An Exposition of the Assemblies Catechisme, by Mr. Nehemiah Beaton, Minister of the Gospel, at Lugarshale in Sussex and copies of letters between G. Nicholetts, Richard Robbins, and others.
- Discourse on the Lord's Prayer, in several secretary hands, probably during the reign of James I, circa 1605-1625 (Box 53)
  Heyworth MS C
- Untitled collection of sermons, 1687 and after (Box 54)
  Heyworth MS D
- Baker, Augustine, 1575-1641. Introduction or preparative to a Treatise of the English Benedictin Mission. By the Venerable Father Baker: manuscript copy, in a single hand, 1734 (Box 55)
  Heyworth MS E
  Inscription on title page: Geo. Fairfax. 1734
- Christian Thoughts for every Day of the month, circa 1720? (Box 56)
  Heyworth MS F
  Translation of Dominique Bonhour, Pensées chrétiennes pour tous les jours du mois
- Barton, William, 1598?-1678. Notes for sermons, circa 1659 (Box 57)
  Heyworth MS G
- Drake, Frances. Commonplace book containing religious notes, reflections, and verses, 1689 (Box 58)
  Heyworth MS H
- Untitled collection of preparatory prayers and notes on texts from Scripture, in Latin and English, 1620s (Box 59)
  Heyworth MS I
- Manuscripts. sermons. 1618 (Box 60)
  Heyworth MS K
  Title from 19th century embroidered case.
- Marsay, Charles Hector de Saint George, marquis de, 1688-1753. The Life of Mr. De Marsay and his Wife, Described by Himself, circa 1750-1770 (Box 61)
  Contemporary manuscript copy of the autobiography of Charles Hector de Saint George, Marquis de Marsay, and his wife, the Lady Clara Elizabeth de Callenberg
- Chilcot, William, 1663 or 4-1711. Practical Treatise concerning Evil Thoughts, 1720 March 16 (Box 62)
- Commonplace book containing philosophical and religious notes in French and English, [175-] (Box 63)
- Spencer, William. A Serious Search of The Sacred Scriptures, 1738 June 23 (Box 64)
- Theological manuscript in Latin, [155-] (Box 65)
- Commonplace book containing sermon notes and religious notes, 1759-1801 (Box 66)
- Religious essays and meditations, [16--] (Box 67)
- Theological manuscript, circa 1790-1820 (Box 68)
- Praelectiones in Epla ad Romanos. A Decemb.11.1688 ad Octob.17.1693, 1688-1693 (Box 69)
- Manuscript fragment with Bible verses, undated (Box 70)
- The Pattern of Pride and Humility in the Two Prayers of the Pharisee and the Publican, [16--] (Box 71)
- Raikes, Robert, 1736-1811. Manuscript in his hand of a sermon written in verse by Peter Pennell, 1785 (Box 72)
- Sermon on predestination, [16--] (Box 73)